For centuries the sacred magic of the Divine Crystal...
幾個世紀以來 神奇水晶的神圣魔法…
blessed our world and its people.
一直保佑著我們的世界和人民
But in time the promise of its power brought war to our lands.
但不久，其權力的承諾 就給我們的土地帶來了戰爭
Lucis, a peaceful kingdom of great magic kept safe by the power of the crystal.
路西斯，一個由水晶魔力保護著的 擁有神奇魔法的和平國家
And Niflheim, a military empire of vast machinery...
尼夫海姆 一個擁有強勢軍事力量的帝國…
made strong by the might of its Magitek.
憑借它的魔擊術變得日益強大
Long has war raged between the two.
兩國之間的戰斗曠日持久
As the years passed, Niflheim marched on nearby nations...
隨著時間的推移 尼夫海姆憑借其不可摧毀的魔力…
driven by its unsurpassed technology.
向鄰國一步步挺進
To defend itself, Lucis raised a magical wall...
為了自我防御 路西斯建立起一座魔法城墻…
the strength of which comes from the crystal itself.
墻的力量來自于水晶本身
Insomnia alone, the crown city and last bastion of Lucian defense...
王都因索莫尼亞 路西斯的最后堡壘…
remained beyond Niflheim reach for many years.
多年來免受尼夫海姆帝國的侵略
Amid the escalating war...
在不斷升級的戰事中…
Prince Noctis of Lucis had come to Tenebrae...
路西斯的王子諾克提斯 來到戴涅布萊國…
to seek healing for a grievous injury.
為了他的病痛來尋求醫治
He made the long journey together with his father, King Regis.
他與他的父王雷吉斯一行遠道而來
Mother, brother, and I, the royalty of Tenebrae...
母后、哥哥，還有我 戴涅布萊國的皇室成員…
had all welcomed their visit.
一同歡迎了他們的到訪
It was then that the fires came, everywhere and all at once.
就在那時 戰火在各個地方同時開始了
In a mere instant, the whole of Tenebrae was ablaze.
轉瞬之間 整個戴涅布萊國火光遍地
Ravus!
雷吉斯！
Mother!
母親！
General Glauca.
格拉烏卡將軍
The Niflheim attack was an attempt on the lives of the visiting Lucian royalty.
尼夫海姆帝國的進攻 是針對來訪的路西斯皇室成員的
Noctis!
諾克提斯！
Please. Help us!
求你了 救救我們！
King Regis!
雷吉斯國王！
Lunafreya....
露娜弗雷亞…
Luna!
露娜！
From that day until this day...
從那天起直到今天…
Tenebrae has been gripped in the iron fist of Niflheim...
戴涅布萊國 一直被尼夫海姆帝國的鐵拳控制…
sworn enemy of Lucis.
宣誓與路西斯為敵
King Regis assembles a force of mighty warriors to combat the imperial menace.
雷吉斯組織了強大的軍隊 來抵御尼夫海姆帝國的威脅
Dubbed the Kingsglaive, they fight relentlessly against Niflheim...
王者之劍 他們憑藉著本國魔法賦予的力量…
empowered by the magic of their sovereign.
與尼夫海姆帝國軍隊英勇作戰
All units, move to secure the Wall.
所有分隊 堅守城墻
If they break through, we're done.
如果他們打進來 我們就完了
What's the hold-up, Crowe?
怎么這么久 克勞？
Crowe! Status?
克勞！ 情況怎么樣？
Almost there.
快要到了
No!
不！
I need help. East wall's going down. Pelna, can you get to me?
我需要支援，東墻已經失守 皮爾納，你能回復我嗎？
Lucis isn't paying us refugees enough...
路西斯讓我們這些難民干這個…
for this.
就給我們這點兒錢
How is this fair?
這算公平嗎？
Nyx, I owe you one.
尼克斯 我欠你一條命
You and everyone else.
你還有其他所有人
We need support on the east flank. Nyx, where are you?
我們東側需要支援 尼克斯，你在哪兒？
I'm on my way.
我馬上到
Pelna, fall back and regroup with the others.
皮爾納，快撤退 和其他人會合
Go easy on the magic, hero.
小心使用魔法 大英雄
You got people waiting for you back home.
家人都在等你回來
I'm worth the wait.
我值得等待
Show-off.
看我大顯身手
Watch your back, Libertus. We got more incoming.
小心后面，利波特斯 敵人更多了
We ain't gonna last much longer.
我們堅持不了多久了
Crowe!
克勞！
Yes!
是的！
All Glaives, fall back. Repeat, all Glaives fall back!
所有劍隊隊員撤退 重復，所有劍隊隊員撤退！
Release the daemon.
放出魔鬼
We can't take down that daemon. I'm ordering a full retreat.
我們無法打敗魔鬼 我要求全體撤退
Get back here alive. That's an order.
活著回來 這是命令
For hearth and home.
為了家園
All units, fall back to the extraction point. Support is inbound.
所有分隊，撤回提取點 支援回程
Nyx! We have to get out of here.
尼克斯！ 我們必須離開這里
- Nyx! We have orders! - Yeah.
-尼克斯，這是命令！ -是的
Help!
救命！
Nyx!
尼克斯！
That idiot.
那個笨蛋
Crowe. We gotta move.
克勞 我們得走了
You gotta be kidding me.
你在開玩笑吧
You know I ain't got the stomach for this crap.
你知道我最受不了這個
Would you rather walk?
你能走嗎？
Come on. Just like Galahd Canyon back home.
快 就像是家鄉的加拉哈峽谷
Libertus!
利波特斯！
Luche, report.
盧徹 報告
The imperial forces look to be withdrawing, sir.
皇室部隊看來正在撤退 長官
Guess I owe you another one.
我想我又欠你的情了
I'll put it on your tab.
我會把它放在你的標簽上的
You just try and get some rest, all right?
你好好休息吧 好嗎？
You disobeyed a direct order to retreat.
你抵抗了撤退的命令
For hearth and home, right, sir?
為了家園 是嗎，長官？
As long as I got strength in my body, I obey that order.
只要我還有一口氣 我就會謹遵命令
Don't fool yourself, Nyx Ulric.
別傻了 尼克斯·烏爾里克
Whatever strength you have is on loan from the king.
無論你有何種力量 都是來自于國王的
You are nothing without him.
沒有他 你一無是處
Await details of your reassignment.
等候你的處理安排吧
Yes, Your Majesty.
是的 陛下
Despite their victory all but assured.
盡管敵人獲得了勝利
A sudden and inexplicable retreat.
一次突然而且莫名其妙的撤退
We are at risk nonetheless, Your Majesty.
我們依然置身于危險之中 陛下
We cannot know when they will strike again.
我們不知道他們什么時候會回擊
Your Majesty, word from the West Gate.
陛下 西門有消息
A man claiming to be an envoy of the empire requests an audience.
一名自稱是敵國使者的人 請求見您
The envoy from Niflheim awaits without, Your Majesty.
尼夫海姆的使者求見 陛下
Hello there.
您好
Hello!
您好！
Good day to you...
很高興見到您…
and you.
還有您
Well met, my dear Lucians.
很高興見到你 路西斯人們
Has Niflheim grown so bold...
尼夫海姆竟然如此毫無顧慮…
that they send the chancellor himself as envoy?
派他們的宰相親自做使者？
And under no guard, at that?
而且只身一人前來？
It is an honor to be recognized by the great King Regis.
能被偉大的雷吉斯國王認出來 真是我的榮幸
Yet permit me to stand on ceremony and introduce myself nonetheless.
而且允許我站在大堂之上 做自我介紹
Ardyn Izunia, Chancellor of Niflheim...
我是阿登·伊祖尼亞 尼夫海姆的宰相…
at your humble service.
愿意為您效勞
And I come to you on this...
我在最吉利的日子來拜訪您…
most auspicious of days to offer terms of peace.
是為了呈上和平協議
Peace?
和平？
As you no doubt surmised...
您肯定猜到了…
that recent maneuver of ours was no strategic retreat.
我們最近的作戰方案 并不是有計謀的撤退
Call it...
請叫它…
a gesture of imperial goodwill.
一次鄰國的示好
Like you, we wish nothing more...
正如你一樣 我們最大的希望就是…
than to bring a swift end to this senseless war.
為這場豪無意義的戰爭畫上句號
Is that so?
果真如此嗎？
It is, indeed.
千真萬確
And we require but a singular compliance.
但是我們要求你們完全的順服
Save your grand Insomnia here.
為了拯救你們的王都因索莫尼亞
Lucis must forfeit all territories to Niflheim rule.
路西斯必須割讓所有的領土
Insomnia!
因索莫尼亞！
The jewel in the crown of the Lucian kingdom.
路西斯王國皇冠上的明珠
How foolish of me to forget.
對了 我怎么能夠忘記
There is just one more trivial thing.
還有一件小事
It concerns your son.
有關于您的兒子
The fetching Prince Noctis of Lucis...
路西斯王國的王子諾克提斯…
and the fair Princess Lunafreya of Tenebrae....
還有戴涅布萊國的美麗公主 露娜弗雷亞…
They are to be wed.
他們要結為夫婦
You seem vexed, Your Highness.
您看起來很苦惱 尊敬的陛下
I assure you, the princess still holds you in the highest regard...
我向您保證 公主一直以來都敬重您…
as she has done all these 12 long years.
這十二年來一向如此
Don't know if anyone's told you...
不知道有沒有人告訴你…
but we don't take kindly to insubordination around here.
但是我們從來不容忍 不服從命令的人
Do yourself a favor, take a look around.
你自己好好看看吧
This is what a hundred years of peace looks like.
這就是百年和平的景象
It's a lasting peace made by the Wall and the Wall alone.
這種和平僅僅靠著一堵墻維持
See, we don't need any of you immigrants...
看見了吧 我們不需要你們這些外來移民…
jumping around, playing war hero.
上躥下跳 充英雄
Hey! Rough day on the gate, huh, Glaive?
嘿！ 今天一戰不順利吧，劍員？
You jerk. It's your fault he got stuck there.
你這個混蛋 是你害的我們被困在那兒
- Not a very nice welcome for a big hero. - Not a very nice outfit for one, either.
-這樣歡迎大英雄可不好 -你這一身裝扮也不好
I think it brings out my eyes.
這樣穿能突出我的眼睛
What'd you put in this?
這里面放了什么東西？
Tastes like a chocobo turd.
吃起來就像是陸行鳥的大便
Hey, shut your trap!
閉上你的臭嘴！
This ain't Galahd. That's the way folks around here like it.
這兒可不是加拉哈 我們這兒的人都喜歡這個
Oh, well. I'm glad to see you're willing to sell out our heritage for a few extra gil.
好吧，我真高興看到你 情愿出賣我們的傳統，只為多賺點錢
Hey, Libertus. You thank Nyx for saving your life yet?
利波特斯 你感謝尼克斯的救命之恩了嗎？
Oh, come on, Crowe. Nyx and I are too close for that.
得了吧，克勞 我和尼克斯誰跟誰呀
He helps me, I help him. That's the way it's always been.
他幫我，我幫他 一向如此
Looks like you got a little help from something else, huh?
看來你從別的地方獲得幫助了 是嗎？
I need all I can get.
我需要所有可能的幫助
For hearth!
為了溫暖！
- And home.
-還有家園 -還有家園
So, Nyx the Gatekeeper. How's the new post treating you?
尼克斯，新任看門人 新工作怎么樣？
Oh, it's amazing. You guys would love it.
簡直棒極了 你們肯定會喜歡的
The gate watch are real sweethearts.
看大門真是太棒了
Yeah, right.
是的 沒錯
We all know they hate us outsiders more than anything.
我們都知道 他們恨我們這些外來人勝過一切
So bored they got nothing better to do.
他們除了恨我們 沒有事情做
Boredom's not so bad.
無聊也沒那么糟
Means there's peace, at least.
至少意味著和平
I'd fight a hundred more wars for Galahdans to know boredom.
為了了解無聊的感受 我愿意為加拉哈人民再戰上百次
Fight all you want.
隨便你
Just don't go dying yet.
只是不要把命丟了
I still owe you.
我還是欠你的
A lot.
欠你很多
Where would the Glaive be without its hero?
王者之劍沒有了英雄 該何去何從呢？
Can you not talk like this while we're drinking, please?
我們喝酒的時候 你能不能別說這些？
We just sent the Niffs running with tails between their legs, right?
我們剛剛把敵人打得落花流水 不是嗎？
They weren't running from us. No, they were toying with us.
他們并不是逃跑了 他們只是在耍我們
Stop being such a buzzkill, Luche. We all know what happened.
別這么掃興，盧徹 我們都知道發生了什么
Did you know they sent an envoy to the Citadel after that?
你們知道他們派出了使者 來到堡壘嗎？
What for? To offer their surrender?
為了什么？ 向我們投降嗎？
- More like demand ours. - What?
-更像是命令我們 -什么？
Demand? My ass!
命令？ 去他們的！
No? Think about it.
不可思議嗎？ 好好想想吧
The empire's got Lucis on its last legs.
敵人已經把路西斯逼到了絕境
It's the perfect time to make demands.
現在正是發出命令的絕佳時機
We are losing this war, Your Majesty.
我們輸定了 陛下
Lucis cannot rely on the Kingsglaive alone.
路西斯不能光靠王者之劍
Accepting the truce may be our best course of action.
接受停戰協議會是我們最好的選擇
You speak of matters beyond the New Wall.
你這樣說完全忘記了我們的新墻
We have no need of a truce here, so long as it stands.
只要新墻還在 我們就不需要什么停戰協議
And if our position worsens, we still have the Old Wall.
即使處境變得更糟 我們還有舊墻
Yes, but this truce will end the fighting altogether.
是的 但是停戰協議可以停止一切戰爭
If only we could compromise...
如果我們肯妥協…
Compromise is unwise.
妥協是不明智的
We know nothing of Niflheim's true intentions.
我們不知道尼夫海姆的真正動機
Do not fool yourselves. The Walls are far from impenetrable.
別傻了 城墻遠非堅不可摧
The paths left to us are few.
我們的選擇所剩無幾
The New Wall draws its power from the throne.
新墻從王座上吸取力量
I am able to sustain it for some years yet, if the kingdom requires it.
如果國家需要 我還可以再支撐它幾年
But the chancellor spoke one truth, if only one.
但是敵國丞相說了一件事實
We are old, and the Old Wall....
我們都老了 舊城墻也…
I cannot command the Old Wall with a weakened hand...
我不能以一只虛弱的手來指揮舊墻…
nor do I have the strength to muster an offensive to turn the tide on this war.
我也沒有力量再掀起反攻的戰斗了
Then let the choice be made, Your Majesty.
請做出最后決定吧 陛下
What are we to protect?
我們要做什么？
Help Mother!
救命 母親！
How come you never lose your lunch like that?
你為什么從來沒有這樣不走運過？
Just doesn't add up.
這些都講不通
Here's this ancient art, secret of the royal family and all that.
這是一種古老的藝術 是皇室的秘密
Libertus! Nyx!
利波特斯！ 尼克斯！
Come here, guys, you gotta see this.
你們都過來 瞧瞧這個
Things were hectic in the capital today...
今天的國會顯得很忙碌…
as the Lucian government announced full acceptance...
因為路西斯政府宣布完全接受…
of what some are criticizing as the unilateral peace terms...
被某些人批評為單方面的…
proposed by Chancellor Izunia of Niflheim.
由尼夫海姆宰相 伊祖尼亞提出的和平條件
The signing of the truce will see power over all Lucian territories...
停戰協議規定 路西斯的所有領土…
transferred to the empire, with the sole exception of Insomnia.
將歸尼夫海姆帝國統治 除了王都因索莫尼亞
In return, Niflheim guarantees the safety of Insomnia and its citizenry...
作為交換，尼夫海姆保證 因索莫尼亞及其居民的安全…
as well as a cessation to all hostilities...
以及停止一切敵對行為…
bringing a decisive end to this long and bitter war.
為這場曠日持久的戰爭畫上句號
All that fighting we did. All for nothing.
我們參加的所有戰斗 一切都是徒勞無功
Glaives. Assemble in the briefing room.
隊員們 報告室集合
Now.
馬上
The king has spoken, and you have heard.
國王已經發言 你們也已經聽到了
All lands beyond the Wall are to be relinquished to the empire.
所有城墻之外的領地 都將割讓給尼夫海姆帝國
Will no regions be spared?
沒有幸存的領地嗎？
- None. - But your home's out there too!
-沒有 -但是你的家鄉也在其中呀！
It is.
我知道
Why would the king do this?
國王為什么這么做？
Because it'll end this damn war.
因為這樣可以結束該死的戰爭
- Crowe. - Sir!
-克勞 -長官！
Prepare to deploy. You're being sent to infiltrate Tenebrae.
做好準備 你要潛入戴涅布萊國
Tenebrae, sir?
戴涅布萊國 長官？
Mission details are classified.
任務細節屬于機密
Report to my office for briefing in 30 minutes.
三十分鐘后 到我的辦公室接受任務…
And, Nyx....
還有 尼克斯…
You're off the West Gate.
你不用再守城門了
You've been reassigned to the castle guard.
你被重新調回堡壘守衛
That is all.
就這些
So this is what you were talking about, Luche?
這就是你要說的嗎 盧徹？
You heard the captain.
你聽到長官說的了
- This wasn't our decision to make. - Not ours to make?
-這又不是我們能決定的 -我們不能決定？
Those are our homes out there! Our people!
那里是我們的家園！ 我們的親人！
You're just gonna go along and abandon them?
你不會就這樣拋棄他們吧？
If we don't go along with them...
如果我們不妥協…
the empire will unleash all hell on Insomnia.
尼夫海姆帝國就會把 因索莫尼亞變成地獄
- We'll unleash it right back at them! - Easy, easy.
-那我們就把他們也扔進地獄！ -別激動，別激動
He's not the enemy.
他不是敵人
Don't you get it?
你不明白嗎？
We're nothing to them.
我們對他們來說 不值一提
Rats, snuck in from beyond the Wall.
膽小如鼠 躲在城墻后面
Sure, they had a use for us...
當然了 他們會利用我們…
when they realized we could work their magic.
因為他們覺得我們可以使用魔法
So they handpicked us from all the other rats out there...
所以他們把我們 從那些老鼠當中挑出來…
and just let us nibble away at his royal majesty's precious power.
讓我們蠶食他寶貴的皇室能力
But as soon as this war's all over...
但是一旦戰爭結束…
it's back to the sewers for all of us.
我們就要回到下水道了
That means you too, hero.
連你也是 英雄
You missing home so much, Libertus, why don't you and Nyx head on back?
你那么想家，利波特斯 為什么不和尼克斯一起回去呢？
I'm sure Niflheim will welcome you with open arms.
我肯定尼夫海姆會張開雙臂歡迎你的
You've got a home out there too.
你的家鄉也在那兒
Or did you forget?
還是說你已經忘了？
Damn it!
該死！
I'm not gonna let it end like this.
我不會袖手旁觀的
It is said sentiment amongst the people is favorable, Your Majesty.
據說民眾的情緒很好 陛下
Most all will welcome this peace.
大部分人都歡迎這樣的和平
If you yourself have not heard their voices...
如果你沒有親耳聽到他們的聲音…
how can you claim to know their hearts?
你怎么能知道他們的真實想法？
What of the mission to Tenebrae, Your Majesty?
去戴涅布萊國的任務怎么辦 陛下？
Is such clandestine action wise?
這樣的秘密行動是否明智？
If discovered, it will only serve to provoke the empire.
如果被發現 這只會激起尼夫海姆帝國的不滿
The empire remains our enemy until the treaty is signed.
在合約簽署之前 尼夫海姆帝國一直是我們的敵人
So long as we are at war...
只要我們還在戰爭中…
His Majesty intends to remain one step ahead of them.
陛下就堅持要領先一步
Of course.
當然
A hairpin? I didn't think you were into that kind of thing.
發卡？ 我覺得你應該不喜歡這種東西
It's not for me. It's a gift for the princess.
不是給我的 是給公主的禮物
But keep that quiet. Nobody's supposed to know.
但是不要張揚 要保密
Well, that's me.
是叫我的
Watch your back out there.
多加小心
I know you're sick of hearing it, but you're like a little...
我知道你不喜歡聽 但是你就像一個…
Little sister to you. Yeah, I am sick of hearing it.
你的小妹妹 我知道，我都聽煩了
Just make sure you come back in one piece, all right?
要保證完完整整地回來 好嗎？
Says the guy in two pieces.
你都不是一個完整的人
Lady Lunafreya, I have left the rear gate open.
露娜弗雷亞公主 我把后門打開了
Thank you.
謝謝你
Must you go?
你必須要走嗎？
Yes.
是的
Then go quickly.
那就快一點兒
I do not recall granting you permission to leave your quarters, Lunafreya.
我記得我沒有允許過你離開這里 露娜弗雷亞
Ravus.
雷夫斯
You are not to leave this room again until the journey to Lucis.
在去路西斯之前 你不準再離開這個房間
It is for your own good.
這是為了你好
My own good?
為了我？
What is truly going on here?
到底發生了什么？
What cause does the empire have to see me wed to Noctis?
尼夫海姆帝國逼我和諾克提斯結婚 有什么用意？
They have offered a peace, and your marriage is the olive branch.
他們要和解 而你們的聯姻就是橄欖枝
You expect me to believe that?
你想要我相信嗎？
What you believe does not concern me.
我不在乎你信不信
What does concern me is you sneaking off...
我在乎的是 你偷偷溜出去…
to go tell our mother's killer about some plot you've dreamt up.
告訴你母親的殺手 一些你自己編造的故事
You are wrong to hate King Regis.
你憎恨雷吉斯國王是不對的
Niflheim killed Mother, not him.
是尼夫海姆殺了母親 不是他
They murdered her and made you their lapdog.
他們殺了母親 讓你成了他們的哈趴狗
It's done.
完畢
An air of jubilation has swept the city in anticipation of the coming armistice.
在等待停戰的期待當中 喜悅的氣氛已經風靡全城…
With only three days remaining until the peace is officially signed into effect...
在和平協議正式生效前 僅僅只剩三天時間了…
throngs of citizens have taken to the streets to show....
居民們踴躍的走上街頭 表示…
Lucis needs your strength, young warriors.
路西斯需要你們 年輕的戰士們
We don't need any of you immigrants.
我們不需要你們這些外來移民
Whatever strength you have is on loan from the king.
不論你有何種能力 都是來自于國王
- You are nothing without him. - Nyx, help Mother.
-沒有他，你一無是處 -尼克斯，救救母親
Selena, get down.
瑟琳娜 趴下
...and the waves of imperial diplomats entering the city.
尼夫海姆的外交官們一波波涌進城市
The princess? Are you certain?
她是公主？ 你確定嗎？
Yes, Your Majesty.
是的 陛下
She was amongst the last of the imperial contingent to enter the city.
她跟隨最后一些帝國來者們 進入了城市
Get in.
上車
I'm reporting to my post now though, sir.
我現在要去報告情況了 長官
New orders.
新任務
Come on. We've got a princess to pick up.
快 我們要去接一位公主
Nice ride, sir.
車不錯 長官
It belongs to the prince.
這是王子的車
We've taken him outside the city.
我們接他出了城
Doesn't he have a wedding to plan, sir?
他不是要準備婚禮嗎 長官？
Cut the "sir" crap.
別再叫我“長官”了
The king has a plan of his own.
國王有自己的打算
Prince Noctis and Princess Lunafreya are to meet far from Insomnia.
諾克提斯王子和露娜弗雷亞公主 要在城外很遠處見面
What's she doing here then?
那她來這兒干什么？
Complicating things.
使局面更復雜
We sent Crowe to find the princess and escort her out of Tenebrae.
我們派克勞去找公主 并且把她護送出戴涅布萊國
We're still trying to figure out what went wrong.
我們還在追查問題出在哪兒
So I know what you think about this war, but what do you think about this peace?
我知道你對戰爭的看法 那你怎么看這場和平呢？
You happy giving up your home?
放棄自己的家鄉 你高興嗎？
It's the king's decision. I owe him for taking me in.
這是國王的決定 因為他重用了我，我欠他的
I was lucky. There are people in Galahd who weren't.
我很幸運 加哈拉有很多人沒有這么幸運
And they need me.
他們需要我
So you're going back?
你要回去嗎？
What good will you be without the king's magic?
沒有國王的魔法 你能怎么幫他們？
Yeah, always wanting to save somebody.
是的 總是想要拯救別人
I get it. Believe me. But it doesn't win wars.
我明白了，聽我說 你這樣不能贏得戰爭
It's not just wanting.
這不只是愿望
It's not just me.
這不只是關于我
Libertus is the one you need to worry about.
利波特斯才是你需要擔心的人
He'll go back if things gets worse.
如果局勢變糟 他肯定會回去
The worst is yet to come.
糟糕的還在后面呢
Do you have any idea who you're stopping?
你知道你要阻止的人是誰嗎？
Open this gate now, and maybe you'll have a job tomorrow.
把門打開 或許明天你還能保住工作
- King's orders. - Are you sure you want to risk...
-這是國王的命令 -你確定你想要挑起…
a diplomatic issue now, of all times?
外交爭端嗎？
I am the personal escort of Lady Lunafreya Nox Fleuret...
我是露娜弗雷亞·諾克斯·芙爾累 公主的私人護衛…
princess of the former Tenebrae and...
戴涅布萊國前任公主…
And our kingdom's beloved bride-to-be.
我們國家廣受愛戴的準新娘
Welcome to sovereign jurisdiction. We'll take care of things from here.
歡迎來到主權管轄區 從現在開始，由我們一手接管
- Forgive me, Captain Drautos. - See Her Highness to the castle.
-不還意思，德勞托斯長官 -送公主去往城堡
I had no idea that you... I wasn't made aware of any...
我完全不知道你… 我不清楚…
- Excuse me. Thank you. - No, you... I must...
-對不起，多謝 -不，你…我必須…
I must... No, I have to clear it with my superiors first.
我必須… 我必須先跟我的上司解釋清楚
Your Highness.
公主殿下
Her Royal Highness, Princess Lunafreya of Tenebrae.
戴涅布萊國的公主殿下 露娜弗雷亞
It has been a long time, Your Majesty.
好久不見了 陛下
Yes.
是呀
Far too long.
太久了
Prince Noctis isn't here, is he?
諾克提斯王子不在這兒 是嗎？
No, my dear. He is not.
是的，親愛的公主 他不在這兒
I am too old to fight this war.
我太老了 不能應戰
I have no choice but to receive the empire and accept their treaty.
我別無選擇 只能接受帝國的要求
Even so...
即便如此…
I had hoped to hold the wedding elsewhere, somewhere safe.
我還是希望婚禮可以在別的地方舉行 安全的地方
I sent one of my Glaive to see you there, but...
我派出一名劍隊成員去找你 但是…
It is not too late.
現在還不晚
I can ready an escort.
我可以安派人護送你
Please, go to my son.
求你了 去找我的兒子
No.
不
Wherever I go, the empire will follow.
不管我去哪兒 帝國都會跟著我
It would only place the prince in greater danger.
這樣只會將王子置于更危險的境地
It is my duty to protect the prince and see his destiny fulfilled.
我的職責是保護王子 幫助他完成他的使命
These 12 years have not changed that.
十二年的時間沒有改變我的初衷
And what of your destiny?
那你的命運嗎？
My duty is my destiny, Your Majesty.
我的職責就是我的命運 陛下
I'm prepared to accept whatever may come to pass.
我已經準備好迎接一切了
So, what do you think?
你覺得怎么樣？
All these lands will be imperial soon.
這些領土很快都會變成帝國的了
Reckon things will get better when them Niffs start calling the shots?
估計那些尼夫海姆人開始發號施令時 局面會變好嗎？
Not one damn bit.
沒有一點兒好東西
Don't matter who's calling the shots.
我才不管是誰掌權呢
Long as they're calling them from behind the Wall...
只要他們是從那面墻后面來的…
ain't nothing gonna change around here.
這里的情形就不會有好轉
Get over here.
過來這兒
All right.
好吧
That's a hand!
這是一只手！
I trust the reunion was a happy one?
我打賭這是一場歡樂的團聚？
Has she been a hostage of Niflheim all this time?
這些年來 她一直都是尼夫海姆的人質嗎？
She is a symbol of the peace. That's all I'm told.
她是和平的象征 我就知道這些
Doesn't sound like it.
聽起來不像
Sounds like she's here for something much bigger than that.
聽起來她的到訪 目的遠非如此
Your orders are to protect her.
你的任務是保護她
Not to look, not to listen, not to think.
不要觀察她，不要傾聽她 更不要去思考
Understood?
明白嗎？
Drautos.
我是德勞托斯
Yes, report.
是的 匯報
Get the hell out of my way. That's my friend you got in there, damn it.
給我讓開路 里面是我的朋友，該死
Sir, you can't go in until the examination has ended.
先生，在檢查結束之前 你不能進去
What examination? What the hell's going on?
什么檢查？ 到底是怎么回事？
Hey, take it easy, big guy.
嘿，放松點兒 伙計
These bastards rushed Crowe in there the moment she got back.
克勞一回來 這些混蛋就把她推進了這里
And now they won't let me in to see her.
現在他們不讓我進去看她
Wait.
等一下
Crowe's personal effects.
克勞的私人物品
Do with them as you see fit.
你看著處理吧
So, what kind of mission did you really send her on?
你到底派她去執行什么任務？
No Glaive winds up dead on a standard escort.
沒有一個劍隊成員 會在執行普通的護送任務時送命
I'll see the armistice does not interfere with a full investigation.
停戰不會影響進行詳盡的調查
She was a good soldier.
她是一名優秀的戰士
Her death will not go unanswered.
她不會白白送死的
What a life, huh?
造化弄人呀 對嗎？
She was brought up an orphan.
她是個孤兒
Run out of her village.
從她的村莊跑出來
I still remember the first time I saw her.
我還記得第一次見到她
Scrawny little thing...
骨瘦如柴的小家伙…
all covered in dirt.
渾身臟兮兮的
Not a friend in the world.
全世界沒有一個朋友
But those eyes....
但是那雙眼睛…
Damn.
該死
There was something about those eyes.
那雙眼睛里有故事
She deserved better.
她不應該就這樣死去
And I would've done anything to give it to...
我愿意為此付出一切…
Libertus, wait.
利波特斯 等一下
Crowe died a Glaive.
克勞死的時候是一名劍隊成員
You can still honor her by fighting as one.
你可以好好戰斗 來紀念她
You're dumber than me sometimes, you know that?
你有時候比我還蠢 你知道嗎？
Don't you get it?
你還不明白嗎？
Lucis killed Crowe.
路西斯害死了克勞
Go back to the castle.
回到城堡
Tell the king there's no peace to be had from throwing the weak to the wolves.
告訴國王 把弱者扔給餓狼是得不到和平的
I'll fight my own fight from here on out.
從現在開始 我要孤身作戰
See you around, hero.
再見了 英雄
A hairpin?
一個發卡？
I didn't think you were into that kind of thing.
我覺得你不會喜歡這種東西的
It's not for me. It's a gift for the princess.
這不是給我的 是給公主的禮物
A most grand reception, King Regis.
真是一場盛大的歡迎儀式 雷吉斯國王
You honor all of Niflheim.
您榮耀了所有的尼夫海姆人
Oh, the honor is ours, Emperor Aldercapt.
榮耀是屬于我們的 艾爾德卡普特國王
You have ventured far to grace us with your presence.
您遠道而來 大駕光臨
It was the very least I could do.
盡微薄之力而已
Tomorrow will be an historic day for both our nations.
對于我們兩國而言 明天將會是歷史性的一天
And your Insomnia is truly a marvel.
您的因索莫尼亞真是一個奇跡
My own cities pale in comparison.
相比之下 我本國的城市黯然無光
I pray we are able to take away much from this visit.
我祈禱這次拜訪能夠滿載而歸
Hello.
你好
I am afraid we were never properly introduced yesterday.
我想今天我們沒有正式認識一下
I'm afraid it's going to have to wait, Your Highness. I'm on guard duty.
恐怕您還要等一下，公主殿下 我正在執勤
Then surely there's no safer place for me to be.
那就更沒有比這里更安全的地方了
May I ask your name?
我能知道你的名字嗎？
Nyx. Nyx Ulric.
尼克斯 尼克斯·烏爾里克
There is something else I wish to ask you, Nyx Ulric.
我還有一件事要問你 尼克斯·烏爾里克
King Regis said he sent one of your order to come find me.
雷吉斯國王說 他派出了你們的一名隊員去找我
I should like to offer my thanks in person.
我想要親自謝謝他
Where might I find this brave soldier?
我到哪兒才能找到這名英勇的士兵？
Oh, I did not...
我不是…
- I am so sorry. - Don't be.
-我很抱歉 -不必
Here.
給你
She was carrying this.
她拿著這個
It was meant for you.
原本是要給你的
For me?
給我？
Keep it.
拿著吧
She would've wanted you to have it.
她肯定希望你能戴上它
I will carry it with me always.
我會一直隨身帶著的
Thank you.
謝謝你
Do you have any idea what this peace means?
你知道這種和平意味著什么嗎？
It means our homes are gone...
它意味著我們的家鄉沒了…
all of them...
所有的…
forever.
永遠消失了
Heard I could find some treaty haters here.
我聽說這兒有一些仇視和平協議的人
I come to the right place?
我來對地方了嗎？
You certainly have.
當然了
Everyone say hello to a man who spends his days...
大家跟這個人打個招呼吧 他的職責是…
in the loyal service of our good king.
在皇室里為偉大的國王效力
"Spent."
“曾經”
Those days are over.
那些日子一去不復返了
I'm done listening to that bastard's lies.
我已經受夠了那個混蛋的謊言
He may sit on a throne, but he ain't no king...
他或許高居王座 但是他不是國王…
least not of mine.
至少不是我的國王
Well, then...
好吧 如此說來…
welcome to the resistance, brother.
歡迎來到反政府組織 兄弟
I hope you're here to talk.
我希望你有話要說
What do you wanna know?
你想知道什么？
Please...
求您…
wherever Noctis is, keep him safe.
無論諾克提斯身在何處 保佑他的安全
That is all I ask.
我別無他求
To what god do you pray?
你向哪個神祈禱？
You, the slave of fate and destiny.
你 命運的囚徒
Abandon your prayers.
放棄你的祈禱吧
The gods do not listen.
神不會聽的
General Glauca. Why are you here?
格拉烏卡將軍 你為什么會在這兒？
You are far too clever to have ever believed in this peace.
你這么聰明 肯定不會相信這次和平談判
Pity you couldn't see your beloved Noctis. You have another purpose.
真可惜你見不到你摯愛的諾克提斯 你還有別的使命
- I'm not here for Niflheim. - No.
-我來這兒不是為了尼夫海姆 -不是
You are here for me.
你來這兒是為了我
You?
你？
I do not understand.
我不明白
Come tomorrow, you will.
明天你就會明白的
Niflheim contingent has left the hotel.
尼夫海姆一行已經離開酒店
Less than three hours until the ceremony.
還有不到三個小時 儀式就要開始了
Bolster the Citadel guard.
加強城堡守衛
Nyx, is the princess with you?
尼克斯 公主和你在一起嗎？
No.
沒有
I'm on duty at the Citadel.
我在守衛城堡
Well, the Niffs just left for the ceremony.
那些尼夫海姆人已經出發前往儀式
And she wasn't with them.
她沒有和他們在一起
- A homing beacon? - Yeah, I'll send the coordinates now.
-歸航信標？ -是的，現在發送坐標
Can you pinpoint a location for me?
你能為我定位嗎？
Sure, but it sounds like a wild-goose chase.
可以 但是聽起來像是追著野鵝到處亂跑
Guess you got some free time on your hands, huh?
我猜你有大把的時間 是嗎？
Guess I do, for better or worse.
是的 不管怎樣吧
Those coordinates are about 20 miles south of Insomnia.
這些坐標都是在因索莫尼亞以南 二十英里的地方
Outside the Wall.
城墻之外
What the hell was Crowe doing all the way out there?
克勞去這些地方干什么？
No, no. They sent her to...
不，不… 他們派她去…
I need another favor, Pelna.
我需要你再幫我一個忙 皮爾納
Pull those coordinates up on the radar and let me know what you find.
在雷達上把這些坐標都調出來 告訴我你發現了什么
On it. You're thinking this is all a big deal now, huh?
收到 你覺得這事關重大嗎？
Yeah, too big to ignore.
是的 不容忽視
- Excuse me, sir. Excuse me. - Hey, hey, hey.
-對不起，先生 -嘿，嘿，嘿
- Whoa, wait a minute. - Stop right there.
-等一下 -停下
Listen up. This is not the gate watch.
聽好了 這里不僅僅是城門守衛
This is the heart of our city, the home of our king.
這里是城市的核心 我們國王的家
The ceremony must not be disturbed.
儀式不容中斷
Neutralize any threat quickly and quietly.
要迅速地、悄悄地擺平一切威脅
Is that understood?
明白嗎？
Yes, sir.
是的 長官
Glaive to command. Are you there, captain?
劍隊成員呼叫 你在嗎，長官？
Urgent.
緊急呼叫
Damn it, Drautos.
該死的 德勞托斯
Jackpot, Nyx. There's a whole fleet of airships sitting at that spot.
重大發現，尼克斯 在這個位置有一整隊飛艇
- Niflheim. - Yup, and from the looks of it...
-尼夫海姆 -是的，看起來…
I'd say they're headed to war.
我覺得他們在準備作戰
- Where's the captain? - Should be at the Citadel.
-隊長在哪兒？ -應該在城堡
There's no answer on his frequency.
他的呼叫器沒有應答
I don't know, must have his hands full with the escort detail.
我不知道 現在肯定忙著護送任務
Pelna, one last favor. I need you to prep the Glaive for action.
皮爾納，最后幫個忙 我需要你啟動王者之劍
What are you talking about?
你在說什么？
You wanna deploy without the captain's order?
你想要不經隊長許可 擅自行動？
Trust me. Just get it done.
相信我 動手吧
Wait, what am I supposed to tell...?
等一下 我該怎么跟他們說…？
Stand down, Glaive.
后退 劍隊隊員
The ceremony is in less than two hours.
儀式還有兩個小時就要開始
We must make ready.
我們必須做好準備
Very well.
很好
Your Majesty.
陛下
A man of the Kingsglaive is here, sire.
一位王者之劍隊員在此
He demands an audience.
要求見您
"Demands"?
“要求”？
- Your Majesty, please. - Halt.
-陛下，求您 -等一下
Give the order to deploy the Glaive.
請下令啟動王者之劍
You.
是你
A Niflheim fleet makes ready for war 20 miles to the south.
城墻以南二十英里 尼夫海姆軍隊已經做好了進攻的準備
An imperial fleet.
帝國的部隊
And they have the princess.
他們挾持了公主
Clarus, post guards outside the treaty room.
克拉魯斯 在簽約室外增派守衛
It will be seen as a lack of faith in the peace.
這樣做將被視為對和平缺乏信心
Which we all harbor.
我們應該避免如此
See it done.
照做吧
We may well have to take Emperor Aldercapt into custody.
我們也許還要 把艾爾德卡普特皇帝置于監禁之下
Detain him?
監禁他？
That would go beyond a new declaration of war.
這絕對等同于再次宣戰
We are still at war, Clarus.
我們仍處在戰爭狀態，克拉魯斯
And you, Nyx Ulric.
還有你，尼克斯·烏爾里克
How soon can the Kingsglaive deploy?
王者之劍多快能夠部署？
On your word, at once.
謹候命令，隨時都可以
Go, then.
那就去吧
Save Luna.
救出露娜
What if this is a diversion?
如果這是調虎離山呢？
Not likely.
不太可能
Tenebrae's princess is onboard.
戴涅布萊的公主在飛艇上
We've got two jobs.
我們有兩件任務
Save her.
救公主
And stop those Niff ships from flying on Insomnia.
阻止尼夫海姆的飛艇 飛臨因索莫尼亞
We go in teams.
我們分組行動
Standard infiltrate and extract.
標準的滲透和拔除行動
Nyx, you command. We'll follow.
尼克斯，你來指揮，我們聽命
The Glaive stands together, captain or no.
王者之劍并肩作戰 無論有沒有指揮官
For hearth.
為了溫暖
And home!
還有家園
We are less than 20 minutes away from the signing of this historic treaty.
距離這項歷史性的停戰協議的簽署 還有不到二十分鐘
I received word of the king's order to deploy.
我接到國王的命令展開部署
I'll see to matters in the city.
我來對付城里的事情
You have your mission, and it won't be easy.
你有你的任務 而且并不輕松
The objective is two-fold.
目標有兩個
Secure the hostage, and stay the enemy advance.
營救人質 阻止敵人的前進
Just be careful.
要小心
One Glaive already died for this princess.
一位劍隊成員已經因公主而犧牲
Niflheim won't give her up easily.
尼夫海姆不會輕易把她交出來的
Team Two.
第二組
Oh, man.
我的天
Hurry up, Nyx!
快點，尼克斯！
Help!
救命！
Over here.
這邊來
Preparing to head below deck.
準備進入甲板下
Do not engage the enemy until instructed.
沒有命令，不要和敵人正面接觸
The ceremony is underway.
慶祝儀式仍在進行
Let's wait and see how Niflheim plays this.
我們等著看尼夫海姆要如何玩
The Kingsglaive have infiltrated the ships.
王者之劍已經滲透進敵艦
So everything's going according to plan.
一切按計劃進行
Ulric reporting. Six Niflheim airships confirmed inbound for Insomnia.
烏爾里克報告 六艘尼夫海姆飛艇正飛往因索莫尼亞
Nyx, this doesn't feel like a war fleet.
尼克斯，這不像是一支作戰艦隊
I think I might've found her. I got a guarded door here.
我應該是找到她了 這里有一扇有守衛的門
Two Niff MTs. What's the plan?
兩個尼夫海姆的甲兵看守 我該怎么辦？
Hold position.
原地待命
Arrived at destination. High possibility of target in the vicinity.
到達指定地點 目標很有可能就在附近
Proceed to secure.
解救人質
It's going to mean a fight.
那就必須動手
Keep it quiet and keep it confined.
小點聲 不要鬧大
Pelna, you're clear to engage. But keep it quiet.
佩爾納，你可以接敵了 但是要小點聲
I'm on my way.
我這就去
Forgive my delay.
請原諒我來遲了
A bit of unforeseen trouble.
有一些意料之外的麻煩
Nothing too vexing, I hope.
希望不是什么大麻煩
A simple theft, nothing more.
只是一個小賊而已
A daring thief, to steal from the king.
賊膽包天 居然偷到國王頭上
Perhaps magical walls and castle gates do not keep all things safe.
也許魔法城墻和城堡大門 也不能保證一切安全
Perhaps.
也許吧
But no matter. That which was taken will soon be returned.
不過不要緊 偷走的很快都要被歸還
Impressive.
難以置信
You are a paragon of kingly composure.
你是王者中沉著的典范
But I must ask...
但是我必須發問
how can you be so sure?
你何以如此確定呢？
Because this thing is no mere trinket.
因為這件東西并不僅僅是裝飾品
It possesses a will all its own.
它有自己的意志
Enough to break any thief's grasp.
足以打破任何盜賊的束縛
That sounds a very fine prize indeed.
聽起來確實是一件不錯的獎品
Not now, damn it.
該死的，不是現在
For me? You shouldn't have.
給我的？ 你太客氣了
Target confirmed. She's unharmed.
目標確認 她一切安好
The Glaives have recovered the princess, Your Majesty.
陛下，劍隊找到了公主
Have you found your thief?
你找到那個賊了嗎？
We have.
找到了
And what was stolen remains intact.
被偷走的東西完好無損
Joyous news.
大好的消息
I am relieved to hear it.
這下我就放心了
Tell me...
告訴我
how heavy a sentence...
在你的帝國里
does the crime of theft carry in your empire?
偷竊將要面對怎樣的刑罰？
Among the heaviest.
最重的刑罰之一
Although there is one...
不過…
exception.
有一個例外
Things are about to get ugly over here.
這里將要亂成一片了
Pelna, get out of there. It's a trap.
佩爾納，快離開 這是個圈套
- What is that? - A curious old law...
-是什么？ -一條有趣的古老法律
I still permit in the outlands.
在邊疆地區仍然有效
A thief who escapes his captor...
如果盜賊能逃脫追捕
can no longer be held to account for his crime.
他就不必再為自己的罪行負責
A warning to the victim.
這是對受害者的警告
Never show weakness, lest you forgo the hand of justice.
不要示弱 以免放松正義之手
Oh, no, good king.
不，尊敬的國王
Far from it.
并非如此
The treaty is now on the table.
協議已經被呈在桌上
The countdown begins to this historical moment.
這個歷史性時刻進入倒計時
It is a warning to the hand of justice itself...
這是對正義之手的警告
never to loose its grip.
永遠不要松開握緊的拳頭
Unit One, secure the perimeter.
第一組，保護外圍
Unit Two, stand your ground.
第二組，原地守衛
Pelna.
佩爾納
One Tenebrae princess, safe and...
戴涅布萊公主安全…
Come on.
快走
The crystal. They're after the crystal.
水晶 他們是沖著水晶來的
There's something going on below deck.
甲板下面出事了
The ship's not going to make it to Insom...
這艘飛艇飛不到因索莫…
You....
你…
What's going on?
出了什么事？
Insomnia is under attack.
因索莫尼亞正在遭受攻擊
Who brought you here?
是誰把你帶來的？
- General Glauca. - You were bait.
-格拉烏卡將軍 -你是誘餌
Us coming here was all part of their plan.
我們到這里來 也是他們的計劃的一部分
Target secured. Request permission to withdraw.
目標被營救 請求準許撤退
Granted. Get to...
準許 去…
The crystal will not serve you.
水晶是不會為你效勞的
Nor you...
也不會為你
once I take it from this accursed city.
我要把它帶離這座被詛咒的城市
It's not the crystal I'm here for.
我來不是為了水晶
The Wall. It's gone.
城墻沒有了
Fall back. It's a trap.
撤退 這是個圈套
What the hell is going on?
到底是怎么回事？
Traitors.
叛徒
What's got into you?
你怎么了？
Come, we must escape while we can.
來吧，趁著還有機會快撤
No, Clarus.
不，克拉魯斯
I fear escape is no longer an option.
恐怕逃跑這條路已經走不通了
General Glauca.
格拉烏卡將軍
Can you make it up? Can you stand?
你能堅持住嗎？
Luche!
盧徹！
What are you doing?
你要干什么？
You gotta be kidding me.
開什么玩笑
They teach piloting back at the royal academy?
皇家學院教授駕駛嗎？
Give me that.
交給我吧
Been a long time since I fought at your side, old friend.
老朋友 我已經很久沒有與你并肩戰斗了
Yes...
是的
but this time it is not your fight.
但這次的戰斗不是你的
If you wish to leave, go now.
如果你想離開 現在就走吧
And abandon my king? I think not.
拋下我的國王？ 絕不
Besides, our magic is bound to you.
另外，我們的魔法都系與你一身
If you fall, Lucis falls.
如果你倒下，路西斯就完了
Then let us once more into the fray...
那就讓我們再次戰斗吧
old friend.
老朋友
You must take me back to King Regis.
你必須帶我去見雷吉斯王
Are you out of your mind? Insomnia's a war zone.
你瘋了嗎？ 因索莫尼亞是戰場
I have a duty. I cannot neglect it.
我有一個責任 不能忘記
- Yeah, I heard all that before. - Then you know we must hurry.
-是啊，這種話我早就聽過了 -那你應該知道，我們必須抓緊
Hurry to do what? Get yourself killed?
抓緊做什么？ 找死嗎？
I do not fear death.
我不害怕死亡
Enough with all this brave princess act.
無畏公主的舉動就免了吧
Just pray this thing will make the trip.
還是祈禱這東西能飛到目的地吧
Clarus.
克拉魯斯
Well, I daresay everything has proceeded according to plan.
我想一切都在照計劃進行
- No? - So it has.
-不是嗎？ -確實如此
We have broken the Wall.
我們已經破壞了城墻
All that remains is to break the city.
現在只剩下摧毀這座城市了
Shall we take our leave, then?
我們應該走了吧？
The sun will soon set.
馬上就要日落了
We need not be here to witness the terrors of the night.
我們不必在這里目擊黑夜的恐怖
The crystal.
神圣水晶
You're going too fast. We have to land.
你飛得太快了 我們必須降落
- You're gonna have to give me a minute. - There is no time. I will go on my own.
-你得再容我一會兒 -沒有時間了，我自己去
You got wings underneath that dress? You can't use magic.
你的衣服下面藏著翅膀嗎？ 魔法是沒用的
Not all miracles are made by magic.
不是一切奇跡都要靠魔法
I do not fear death.
我不害怕死亡
What I fear is doing nothing and losing everything.
我所怕的是 什么也不做，因而失去一切
Oh, come on.
沒辦法
You can thank magic for that miracle, Your Highness.
殿下，這個奇跡靠的還是魔法
The reckoning is at hand.
到了清算的時候了
Dawn of a new age.
新時代的曙光就在眼前
You have the crystal. What more would you take from me?
你已經拿到了水晶 你還想從我這拿走什么？
The Ring of the Lucii.
路西斯之戒
I lost my mother, my country, my birth-right.
我失去了我的母親、我的國家 我與生俱來的權力
Niflheim was the only life left to me.
尼夫海姆是我唯一的希望
But all of that was for this.
但這一切都是為了它
The ring belongs to me now.
這枚戒指現在屬于我了
Hear me, Lucian kings of old, for I am Ravus Nox Fleuret...
側耳聽吧，古時的路西斯眾王 我是雷夫斯·諾克斯·弗洛雷
and none is more worthy of your power than I.
世間唯我配得擁有你們的能力
No. Why?
不…為什么？
Why do you refuse me?
你們為什么拒絕我？
Look out.
當心
Quickly, through here.
快，從這出去
This leads to a hidden passageway.
這里通往一條秘密通道
Follow it.
沿著通道走
Once you are away, make for Altissia.
離開之后 前往艾爾提夏
Noctis awaits you there.
諾克提斯在那里等著你們
- Your Majesty. - You knew this was coming...
-陛下 -你早知道這些事將要發生…
Yes. But it was the only way to draw their wrath from Noctis.
是的，但只有這樣 才能讓他們的怒氣轉離諾克提斯
Is that the way of our king?
這就是我們的王嗎？
Sacrifice Lucian sons to save his own?
犧牲路西斯眾子來救他自己的命？
To save the world.
是為了救這個世界
See Luna safely to Altissia.
把露娜安全送到艾爾提夏
This is not an order from a king to his Glaive.
這不是國王向劍隊發出的命令
This is a plea from one man to another. Please, Nyx Ulric, keep her safe.
這是一個男人向另一個男人的懇求 拜托，尼克斯·烏爾里克，保她安全
For the future of all.
為了所有人的未來
The future?
未來？
Here.
給
Take this.
拿著
It is time it passed to another's keeping.
是時候把它交給別人保管了
No, please. Stop.
不，求你住手
- Get back. - Please. Don't leave us.
-回來 -求你了，別離開我們
I know your mother would wish the same as me.
我知道 你的母親與我有同樣的企盼
That you and Noctis live happily.
就是你和諾克提斯幸福地生活
All those years captive because I failed you.
你被囚禁這么多年 都因我的失敗
Not again.
但這次不會了
Locked doors will seal your fate no longer.
緊鎖的大門再也不能捆綁你的命運
King Regis....
雷吉斯國王
Our hope goes with you now, Nyx Ulric. Godspeed.
我們的希望系于你的身上 尼克斯·烏爾里克…祝你成功
Behold the King of Lucis...
看啊，路西斯的王
who hoarded tranquility within his precious walls.
躲在寶貴的城墻后面 積累著平安
Where is your tranquility now, king?
你的平安去哪了，陛下？
Here is your peace, by steel's swift descent.
你的平安來了 靠的是鋼鐵的猛然落下
Go.
快走
No. We must get away from here.
不，我們必須快點離開這兒
It is what your king wanted.
這才是你的國王的意愿
Lady Lunafreya has escaped with the ring.
露娜弗雷亞帶著戒指逃跑了
Find her at once.
馬上找到她
She is not to leave the city.
她不能離開這座城市
- Ulric to command. Come in, captain. - Footage of the perpetrators...
-烏爾里克呼叫指揮官，隊長，回話 -附近一架監控攝像頭…
was captured by a nearby surveillance camera.
拍下了罪犯的影像
Here are images of the six suspects.
以下是六名嫌犯的圖像
One has been identified as Galahdian refugee, Libertus Ostium...
其中一人被確認為加拉哈難民 利波特斯·奧斯提姆
a former member of the Lucian Kingsglaive.
前路西斯王者之劍成員
Hey, come here. Come here.
嘿，起來
I got you, I got you. You're all right.
我來救你 你沒事了
You're okay.
你沒事了
It's fine.
沒事了
We're free.
我們自由了
We're free now.
我們現在自由了
We're free? What do you mean, "We're free"?
我們自由了？ 你這是什么意思？
The empire. They promised.
帝國…有承諾
This district's ours.
這個地區是我們的
All the refugees.
是我們這些難民的
It's our new home.
這是我們的新家園
- The empire? You went in with Niflheim? - Here.
-帝國？你投靠了尼夫海姆？ -給你
Take this. Meet up with the others.
拿著它 與其他人會合
You're the hero of our revolution, brother.
你是我們的革命英雄，兄弟
Damn it.
該死
This guy just doesn't know when he's beat.
這家伙還不知道他被擊中了
- Can you drive? - I can try.
-你會開車嗎？ -我可以試試
I'll be right back.
我馬上就回來
No warping for you this time, hero.
這次飛不回去了，英雄
Give me the wheel. Go.
把方向盤給我 讓開
You are without your magic.
你的魔法沒了
You noticed that, huh? It must have died with the king.
你也注意到了？ 一定是因為國王死了
You're making a mess of my city, Glaive.
你把我的城市搞得一團糟，劍隊隊員 我告誡過你，不要逞英雄
Leave the ship to me.
把飛艇交給我吧
Looks like you got a royal fare to see to.
你還有皇家的事情要辦
Move it.
出去
Maybe not all miracles are made by magic.
也許并非所有的奇跡都是出于魔法
Oh, great.
太好了
The hell did you do to piss these things off?
你做了什么 惹得這些家伙如此生氣？
It's not me they're after. It's the ring.
它們追的不是我 而是戒指
What's so special about this ring? Don't tell me the future's riding on it.
那枚戒指有什么特殊的？ 別告訴我未來就靠它了
He who wears the ring communes with the Lucii...
戴上這枚戒指的人 可以與路西斯人溝通
- ...and commands great power. - What kind of power?
-并駕馭強大的力量 -什么樣的力量？
A forbidden one. Sealed within the ring, long ago.
禁忌的力量 很久以前被封在這枚戒指中
The Old Wall. I thought that was just a bedtime story.
舊城墻 我以為那只是睡前故事
I can assure you it is not.
我可以擔保 那不是睡前故事
But the Lucii grant their power only to those they deem worthy.
但路西斯人只將這種力量 交與他們認為配得的人
So that guy who tried it on back there...
所以剛才那個戴上戒指的人…
I guess he wasn't deemed worthy.
我猜他們認為他不配
That was my brother.
那是我哥哥
These 12 years have changed Ravus.
這十二年改變了雷夫斯
He is bound by the past, and lost in his lust for power.
他癡迷于過去 迷失在對權力的貪欲中
How the hell did they find us?
它們是怎么找到我們的？
Your hairpin. They're tracking it. Give it to me.
你的發卡被它們追蹤 把它給我
I had a little sister once. She was killed when the empire came.
我曾有一個小妹妹 它在帝國入侵時被害
I couldn't save her.
我救不了她
I was as helpless then as I am now.
那時的我 就像現在一樣無助
I couldn't show her the future she wanted.
我無法讓她看到自己向往的未來
True power is not something that is found by those who seek it.
真正的力量 是無法被那些尋求它的人發現的
It is something that comes to those who deserve it.
它會找到配得上擁有它的人
Your sister wanted you to see a future as well.
你的妹妹也希望你能看到未來
Anyone would wish the same for family they love.
任何人對他們所愛的家人 都有同樣的希望
You don't pull any punches, do you?
你是不會放過任何機會的，是吧？
I'm over here.
我在這
Do you hear me? Repeat, this is Drautos.
聽見了嗎？ 我重復一遍…我是德勞托斯
Can you hear me? Over.
能聽得見嗎？ 完畢
Your timing's impeccable, captain.
你真會挑時候啊，隊長
If the Lucii are real...
如果真有路西斯人
they sure don't seem to mind their city getting torn apart.
他們確實不在乎 自己的城市被撕碎
You're to rendezvous and regroup. Understood?
你要重新歸隊 明白嗎？
Might not be so easy, captain.
也許沒那么容易，隊長
My wings have been clipped, if you didn't know.
也許你還不知道 我的翅膀被剪了
Ulric. Are you all right?
烏爾里克，你還好吧？
I'm not dead, if that's what you mean, sir.
我還沒死 你是想問這個嗎，長官？
Head for Section D as soon as you can.
盡快前往D區
I'll have an evacuation team ready.
我讓營救隊準備好
Don't suppose you could meet me at the gate.
看來我們不能在城門見面了
I'd kind of like to get the hell out of this city.
我確實很想離開這座城市
Imperials hold all exits. There's no way through.
帝國的軍隊控制了所有出口 沒有能夠沖出去的地方
I'll meet you at Section D.
我們在D區見面
Cut all radio contact until then. And make sure you get there.
在此之前切斷一切無線電聯絡 你要保證到達那里
It's a date, sir.
這是一次親密約會，長官
Ain't no turning back now.
沒有回頭路了
Status report.
狀況報告
Ulric killed some good men.
烏爾里克殺死了一些人
- What about the ring? - We don't have it yet.
-戒指呢？ -還沒拿到
This is Glauca. King Regis is dead.
我是格拉烏卡 雷吉斯國王死了
The ring is on its way to Section D.
戒指即將前往D區
We must recover the ring to realize our goal.
我們必須找到戒指 實現我們的目標
If Ulric or the princess get in the way, take them out.
如果烏爾里克或是公主出手阻止 那就干掉他們
Reclaim our hearth and home.
奪回我們的溫暖與家園
"Hearth and home"?
“溫暖與家園”？
Libertus, come in.
利波特斯，回話
Where are you? Are you all right?
你在哪？你沒事吧？
I'm fine.
我很好
On the way back to base now.
我正在回基地的路上
We need you to head to the junction in Section D.
我們需要你前往D區的交叉路口
We're gonna join with another unit, make a clean sweep of the place.
我們將與另一組人會合 把那個地方打掃干凈
We're one step away from realizing this revolution.
我們離革命勝利只差一步了
Let's not let Pruvia's death be in vain.
不要讓普魯維亞白白死去
We'll be waiting for you, hero.
我們等著你，英雄
- Don't move until I say it's safe, all right? - I won't.
-在我說“安全”以前不要動 -明白
Ulric, reporting.
烏爾里克報告
I have the princess.
我把公主帶來了
She's alive and well.
她活的好好的
- No! - Get out of here.
-不！ -快離開
You've got some fight in you, Nyx, I'll give you that.
你還真能打呀，尼克斯 這一點我承認
Run. Now.
快跑
I can't believe you're still moving with that hollowpoint in you.
我沒想到 你身中一枚空尖彈頭，居然還能動
All Crowe could do was scream, when one tore her insides apart.
空尖彈頭撕裂克勞體內的時候 她只能慘叫
- Why'd you do it? - Because the Kingsglaive is nothing.
-你為什么要這么做？ -因為王者之劍什么也不是
An old man's battle fodder...
作一個老家伙的炮灰
sent to die in Insomnia's war...
為了因索莫尼亞的戰爭而死
while our homes are bound and shackled.
而我們的家園卻在枷鎖之中
Niflheim took your home.
尼夫海姆奪去了你的家園
Took all our homes!
奪去了我們所有人的家園
Nothing will ever change that.
任何事都不能改變這一切
You never were too smart.
你永遠不夠聰明
You could've had a new future with the empire.
你本來可以在帝國擁有嶄新的未來
There's nowhere to run, princess.
你無處可逃了，公主
The ring.
戒指
Give it to me.
把它給我
So many dead over so simple a thing.
如此多人 為了這樣一件小東西而死
But why? For what?
為什么？為了什么？
Power.
力量
Untold power, beyond the control of someone like you.
無盡的力量 像你這種人是無法駕馭的
Captain.
隊長
Nyx.
尼克斯
It's over. The daemons are unleashed.
一切都結束了 惡魔已經被釋放
Lucis is fallen.
路西斯淪陷了
Surrender the ring.
交出戒指
Plan on giving those kings a piece of your mind, princess?
想把自己的想法告訴那些國王嗎？
You got a destiny to take care of here, remember?
記得嗎？你在這里還有未盡的使命
Besides, didn't anyone tell you?
另外，有沒有人告訴你
I'm the hero around here.
我才是這里的英雄
Show yourselves, kings of Lucis.
現身吧，路西斯的眾王
You call upon the wards of this world's future, mortal.
你呼求這個世界的未來，凡夫俗子
And if you come lusting for our power, you must first stand in our judgment.
如果你貪戀我們的力量 就必須首先經受我們的審判
How long will you do nothing whilst Insomnia burns?
你們要旁觀因索莫尼亞焚燒到幾時？
Old or new, or whatever it is.
老的少的 無論你們是誰
Summon your Wall.
筑起你們的城墻
You do not command us.
你不能命令我們
Yours is not even royal blood.
你根本就不是皇室血脈
It does not fall to us to guard your city.
保護你們的城市 根本不是我們的職責
Man is a fool creature...
人類是愚蠢的生物
clinging to his past and cowering from his future.
緊緊抓住過去 對未來畏縮不前
Wasting his strength on bygone days.
為了已經逝去的日子而白費力氣
And what future are you wards of?
你們又有什么未來？
So shortsighted.
太短視了
And cursed never to rise above it.
并且被咒詛 永遠不能超越其上
Wait.
等一下
I have seen what this brave soul is prepared to do.
我見過這個勇敢的靈魂準備做什么
He, too, seeks to safeguard the future.
他也想保護未來
Your Majesty.
陛下
Very well, young king. We will weigh your warrior's worth.
好吧，年輕的國王 我們將考量你的武士的價值
But our boon does not come cheap.
但我們的恩惠并不廉價
The cost is a life. His or hers.
代價是一條生命 他的、或是她的
No.
不
To hell with your power.
去你的力量吧
I'm not here for it.
我不是為此而來的
I only came to tell you, you are no kings.
我只是來告訴你們 你們不是王
Your worth has been weighed and found wanting.
你的價值已經被考量 結論是不夠格
Now burn.
燃燒吧
You're going to lose your precious ring.
你將失去那寶貴的戒指
But it's not too late to save it.
但拯救它還為時未晚
You mean to barter for your life.
你要用它交換生命嗎？
No, no.
不
My life is nothing.
我的生命不算什么
Giving a future to those who want to see it...
給那些希望看到未來的人一個未來
is everything.
這才是最重要的
You do not fear, even if that future is doomed.
你并不害怕 即使那個未來已經注定滅亡
If that sentiment is not false, perhaps you are worthy.
如果這份感情并非虛假 那么也許你還有些價值
We will grant you our light.
我們將授予你我們的光
But know it will set when the sun rises.
但是你要知道 太陽升起之后，它就將消失
And the price for it will be your life.
為此付出的代價將是你的生命
You guys drive a hard bargain.
你們可真會討價還價
Where do I sign?
我在哪簽字？
I could get used to this.
等我慢慢習慣吧
Nyx....
尼克斯
- I'm sorry. - Don't be.
-對不起 -不必
You saved me.
你救了我
Now I owe you.
現在我欠你的
For a change.
換換也好
I'm gonna need another favor.
我需要你再幫一個忙
Meet Lunafreya Nox Fleuret, our prince's beloved bride-to-be.
這位是露娜弗雷亞·諾克斯·弗洛雷 我們的王子未來的新娘
And she has the future of the world in her hands.
她的手中掌握著這個世界的未來
Keep her safe, get her out of Insomnia.
保護她的安全 帶她離開因索莫尼亞
Oh, I almost forgot. You'll need this.
差點忘了 你需要這個
Give Prince Noctis my regards.
代我向諾克提斯王子致意
Libertus will take care of you from here.
從現在開始 利波特斯將照顧你
Have a safe journey, Your Highness.
一路平安，殿下
- What will come of you? - What the hell are you doing?
-你怎么辦？ -你要干什么？
Following the kings' orders.
遵循眾王的命令
I will see the ring to Noctis.
我會把戒指交給諾克提斯
The future will be safe. I swear it.
未來將會平安 我發誓
Planning on punching your way out of the city? Keep it.
你想靠拳頭殺出城嗎？ 留著吧
- Now we're even. - No.
-現在我們扯平了 -不
We'll settle up once you're back in Galahd.
等你回到加拉哈在算賬
Me and everyone else will be waiting for you.
我和其他所有人等著你
I'm counting on you...
全靠你了
hero.
英雄
- Buckle up, princess. - My life is in your hands.
-系好安全帶，公主 -我的命在你手中
So, the power of the Lucii returns.
路西斯人的力量又回來了
No matter. You are out of time.
沒關系 你沒有時間了
For you, I'll make some.
為了你，我可以擠一些時間
What can you hope to do?
你有什么希望？
One man against an empire.
一人對付整個帝國
Against the daemons.
對付眾惡魔
How will you save Insomnia with no wall to protect you?
沒有城墻保護 你怎么拯救因索莫尼亞？
You've got it all wrong. I'm not fighting to save Insomnia.
你完全錯了 我不是為了拯救因索莫尼亞而戰
So this is the might of the Old Wall.
這就是強大的舊城墻
Marvelous. Truly marvelous.
不可思議 真的不可思議
Why'd you do it?
你為什么要這么做？
Lucis. Niflheim.
路西斯、尼夫海姆
It isn't who we fight for that matters, only what.
重要的不是為誰而戰 而是為了什么
We fight for our homes. That is where our allegiance lies.
我們為了家園而戰 這才是我們的忠誠所在
That's not something you see every day.
這種景象難得一見
Oh, such a pitiable waste.
多么可惜的浪費
All those beautiful city streets, all laid to unsightly ruin.
這些漂亮的街道 變成丑陋的廢墟
- I will return to Niflheim. - So soon?
-我要返回尼夫海姆 -這么快？
The crystal is ours.
神圣水晶已經是我們的了
Finish this...
把這里的事弄完
and see the daemons disposed of.
讓惡魔們隨意處置吧
As you command.
謹遵圣命
Such a pitiable waste.
多么可惜的浪費
How could you serve the empire?
你怎能為帝國賣命？
After everything they did?
他們都做了些什么！
I do not fault them for taking what was given.
我不怪他們 奪得別人的饋贈
I fault the man who gave it.
我怪罪那些饋贈他們的人
The man who cowered behind his wall...
那個躲在城墻之后的人
and abandoned us to save his throne and his son.
拋棄了我們 只為保住他的王位和兒子
Give me the ring, and our homes will be free again.
把戒指給我 我們的家園將重獲自由
The empire has promised it.
皇帝承諾如此
I don't see much of a future on the other side of that promise.
在這個承諾上 我看不到什么未來
Don't be a fool.
別作傻瓜
Save your friends.
救救你的朋友們吧
Give your dead sister peace.
也讓你死去的妹妹安息
What do you fight for if not that?
否則你為什么而戰？
Hang on. This could get bumpy.
坐穩了 前面很顛簸
Drautos.
德勞托斯
Here, take the wheel.
給，你來開車
Floor it!
油門踩到底！
- Libertus! - Just keep your foot on the gas.
-利波特斯！ -踩住油門別放
You're all right?
你沒事吧？
I'll be waiting for you, hero.
我等著你，英雄
What of your kings' power now?
你那眾王的力量怎么了？
They've given you a burden you cannot hope to bear.
他們交給你的重擔 你根本擔不起
I told you before.
我曾經告訴你
Just wanting doesn't win wars.
僅憑愿望 是無法贏得戰爭的
For the honor of my home, I fought and killed under a king I loathed.
為了我的家園的榮耀 我為了一位我所厭惡的國王四處攻殺
And still he betrayed me.
但是他仍然背棄了我
He betrayed us all.
他背棄了我們所有人
We fought for the same thing. All of us.
我們都在為同樣的東西而戰
But you've looked too long on the past.
但你對過去看得太多
You're blind to the future.
對未來完全無視
Predictable.
太容易被猜透了
Unlike you, I learn from history.
和你不一樣 我從歷史中學習
But you're a slave to the past.
但你是往事的奴隸
A man's past is his pride.
一個人的往事是他的榮耀
No.
不
My pride is shaping the future.
我的榮耀在于塑造未來
Looks like I'm gonna owe him big.
看來我要虧欠他許多了
We're almost there.
我們就快到了
Almost.
快到了
King Regis did what he did for the future.
雷吉斯王為了未來 做了他該做的事
Because of him...
因為他
there's still hope for our homes.
我們的家園還有希望
Hope....
希望…
Not the worst way to go.
這樣死去倒也不算太壞
Rule well, young king.
好好統治吧，年輕的國王
We should move.
我們該走了
It ain't safe here either.
這里也不安全
Hey.
嘿
Don't worry about Nyx.
別擔心尼克斯
He can take care of himself.
他會照顧好自己的
Come on.
走吧
No.
不
We must part ways here.
我們必須分開了
What?
什么？
I can hardly travel in secrecy alongside so great a hero.
有你這位大英雄為伴 我怎么能秘密前行？
And I, too, have a promise to keep to Nyx.
我也要為尼克斯信守一個承諾
I pray you two see each other again soon.
我祈禱你們倆很快會重逢
Yeah.
是啊
Me too.
我也想
Thank you, Libertus.
謝謝你，利波特斯
Hey, queen!
嘿，王后！
You and the king are always welcome in Galahd.
隨時歡迎你們到加拉哈來
Me and Nyx will be waiting for you.
我和尼克斯會等著你們
It's been some while.
已經有很長時間了
Do you remember the last time you saw Lady Lunafreya?
你還記得上一次看見露娜弗雷亞夫人 是在什么時候嗎？
About 12 years ago.
大概十二年前
That would make you 8?
也就是說 在你八歲的時候？
- You were kids. - Hope she hasn't gotten her hopes up.
-你們那時還是小孩子 -希望她別抱太大希望
Why not? Calm yourself.
為什么不？ 你要鎮靜
Try and keep it together when you meet her.
見到她時 你別太激動
- She'll expect to see a fine, young prince. - Tell me something I don't know.
-她想見到一位得體的年輕王子 -你以為我不知道嗎？
We don't have time for all that.
我們沒有時間扯這些
But this is your wedding we're talking about, Noc.
但我們談論的是你的婚禮
Knew that too.
這句也算
You really gotta calm down.
你真的需要冷靜一下
What do you mean, "Uh-oh"?
“啊哦”是什么意思？
I think I know.
我想我明白